Finding Aid for Albert A. Stanley papers, ca. 1890s-1932
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Albert A. Stanley papers ca. 1890s-1932
Stanley, Albert A. (Albert Augustus), 1851-1932.
3 linear feet (in 4 boxes)
8642 Aa 2
Professor of music and director of the University Musical Society at University of Michigan. Correspondence, articles, lectures, speeches, autobiography, and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was received from the University of Michigan Library (donor no. 1278 ), from Earl V. Moore (donor no. 3723 ) and from Mrs. Albert A. Stanley (donor no. 5535 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Albert A. Stanley was born at Manville, Rhode Island, on May 25, 1851. At the age of fourteen years he became organist at the Congregational Church at Slaterville, Rhode Island. Three years later, he was selected to be organist at the Church of the Medeator in Providence. From 1871 to 1875 he studied abroad, graduating from the Leipzig Conservatory. In his early career, Stanley excelled as organist, conductor and composer.
In 1888, James B. Angell, President of the University of Michigan, invited Stanley to the university as professor of music and director of the University Musical Society. As a result of his efforts, the University School of Music came into existence as successor to what up to that time had been known as the "Ann Arbor School of Music." During his preliminary years in Arbor, Stanley also organized the community's concert activities, and gradually inaugurated noteworthy series of public musical programs. In 1894, as the closing event in the season's series of concerts, Stanley initiated the first Annual May Festival. Within a relatively short time the Ann Arbor May Festival became recognized as one of the great festivals of the world. In the Festival series and in the Choral Union Concert series, which each year preceded the Festival program, many of the world's most celebrated artists performed.
Stanley's great influence in the field of music was not limited to his activities at the University or in the city of Ann Arbor. He also took a prominent part in the state, national and international musical affairs, serving as treasurer and twice as president of the Music Teachers National Association. He was a founder of the College of Musicians, president of the American Section of the International Musical Society, and twice president of the Michigan Music Teachers Association. In 1890, the University of Michigan conferred on him the honorary degree of Master of Arts, and in 1930 the degree of Doctor of Music. He died May 19, 1932.
The Stanley collection consists mainly of manuscripts of his articles, lectures, and speeches on musical topics. There is, in addition, Stanley's research material, including musical notes and analyses, notes intended to accompany illustrations of musical instruments found in the Stearns Collection of Musical Instruments at the University of Michigan, and scrapbooks containing concert programs featuring Stanley and his work. Stanley's autobiography, "Echoes of a busy life or reminiscences of a professor emeritus" is a valuable source of personal information.
Subjects:
Music--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Musical instruments.; Stearns Collection of Musical Instruments.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Ann Arbor May Festival.; University of Michigan. School of Music.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Composers.; Musicians.; Organs.; Stanley, Albert A. (Albert Augustus), 1851-1932.; Stanley family.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Contributors:
Holst, Gustav, 1874-1934.; Kelsey, Francis W. (Francis Willey), 1858-1927.; Sousa, John Philip, 1854-1932.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Personal
  - Photographs (Box 1)
    - Portraits and photos of Stanley with his wife and seated at an organ, ca. 1890s-ca. 1920s (Box 1)
    - Family members, groups, musical instruments, etc. (Box 1)
  - Autobiography, "Echoes of a busy life or reminiscences of a professor emeritus", 15 folders (Box 1)
    (microfilm copy available)
  - Correspondence, 1913-1932 and undated, 3 folders (Box 1)
    (include letters from Francis W. Kelsey, John Philip Sousa, and Gustav Holst)
  - International Musical Society correspondence and reports, 1907-1911 (Box 1)
  - Last will and testament, 1918 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous texts, sketches, poems (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous and personal (Box 1)
  - Reviews of "Greek Themes in Modern Musical Settings" 1924 (Box 1)
- Manuscripts of articles, lectures and speeches
  - "Candid considerations of a difficult problem" (Box 1)
  - "Provincial music festival in the United States" (Box 1)
  - "Graduate work in music in America" (Box 1)
  - "Folk songs" (Box 1)
  - "How to listen to a symphony" (Box 1)
  - Commencement address, University of Michigan School of Music, 1920 and 1921 (Box 1)
  - "Modern Concepts of the Structure of Music" (Box 1)
  - "The function of the concert room" (Box 1)
  - Talks on worship music (Box 1)
  - "Literature and music" (Box 1)
  - "Patriotism in music" (Box 1)
  - "Music as an expression of the Spirit of the Age" (Box 1)
  - "Bayreuth and the Wagner Festival" (Box 1)
  - Music and the University (Box 1)
  - Frederick Stearns (Box 1)
  - Title unknown (Box 1)
  - "Modern and Colonial" paper of Mrs. Albert A. Stanley read before the Daughters of the American Revolution, 1907 (Box 1)
- Research and miscellaneous
  - Illustrations of musical instruments (Box 4)
  - Notes for illustrations of musical instruments (Box 4)
  - Musical scores (fragmentary) (Box 4)
  - Newspaper clippings largely concerning the May Festival (Box 2)
  - Manuscript of Catalogue of the Stearns Collection (fragmentary) (Box 2)
  - Printed material, including programs (Box 2)
  - Musical notes (Box 2)
  - Evolution of musical instruments (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous notes, 12 folders (Box 2)
  - Musical analyses, 6 folders (Box 2)
  - Scrapbooks containing programs of musical performances, 8 volumes (Box 3)
  - Commemorative volume presented to A.A. Stanley on the occasion of the Twentieth Annual May Festival, 1913 (Box 3)
    (includes medallion)